<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="taxi_driver_script.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--START PART 2-->
<!--Part 2 Markup by E. Larson-->
<root>    
    <script>

40.
CONTINUED:
<d who="pal">PALANTINE
<char who="trav">Travis</char>, what single thing would you
want the next President of this
country to do most?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I don't know, sir. I don't follow
political issues much.</d>
<d who="pal">PALANTINE
There must be something...</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="thinks">(thinks)</desc>
Well, he should clean up this city
here. It's full of filth and scum.
Scum and filth. It's like an open
sewer. I can hardly take it. Some
days I go out and smell it then I
get headaches that just stay and
never go away. We need a President
that would clean up this whole mess.
Flush it out.</d>
<narr><char who="pal">Palantine</char> is not a Hubert Humphrey-type professional
bullshitter, and <char who="trav">Travis'</char> intense reply stops him dead in his
tracks. He is forced to fall back on a stock answer but tries
to give it some meaning.</narr>
<d who="pal">PALANTINE
<desc par="after a pause">(after a pause)</desc>
        I know what you mean, <char who="trav">Travis</char>, and
it's not going to be easy. We're
going to have to make some radical
changes.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="turning the wheel">(turning the wheel)</desc>
Damn straight.</d>
</scene>
        
<scene>
<loc ext="true">EXT. BARCLAY HOTEL</loc>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS'</char> taxi pulls up in front of the Barclay Hotel.
<char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> and <char who="side">AIDE</char> get out of the cab. <char who="side">SECOND AIDE</char> stays in
back seat a moment to pay <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>.
<char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> looks in front window of cab momentarily and nods
goodbye to <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>.</narr>
<d who="pal">PALANTINE
Nice talking to you, <char who="trav">Travis</char>.</d>
(CONTINUED)
41.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="calling back">(calling back)</desc>
Thank you, sir. You're a good man,
sir.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis'</char> taxi departs.
<char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> and <char who="side">AIDES</char> walk up carpet to the St. Regis.
<desc shot="close">CAMERA CLOSES IN on <char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> as he stops, turns back and
watches <char who="trav">Travis'</char> departing taxi.</desc>
<char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> turns back and ascends the hotel steps with his
<char who="side">AIDES</char>.</narr>
</scene>
        
<scene>
<narr><loc ext="true">EXT. MANHATTAN STREET</loc> - EARLY MORNING
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, dressed to the teeth, walks brightly down the
sidewalk. His face is frehsly shaved, his hair combed, his
tie straightened.
He pauses in a store window to check his appearance.
Under his arm he carries the gift-wrapped Kristofferson record
album.
<loc>OUTSIDE PALANTINE HEADQUARTERS</loc>
    <char who="bets">BETSY</char>, smartly dressed, waves goodbye to another <char who="side">CAMPAIGN
WORKER</char> and walks out the door to greet him.
A SHORT WHILE LATER, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> and <char who="bets">BETSY</char> are walking down
Broadway toward Times Square. <char who="bets">BETSY</char> does not let their bodies
touch as they walk although <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> contemplates edging closer
to her.
<char who="bets">Betsy</char> has opened the package and is admiring the record -
or, rather, <char who="trav">Travis'</char> sentiment behind giving it.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> looks around himself with pride: This is a moment in
his life - one of the few.</narr>
<d who="bets">BETSY
You didn't have to spend your money -
?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="interrupting">(interrupting)</desc>
    He'll, what else can I do with it
all?</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> notices that the seal on the record has not been broken.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
42.
CONTINUED:
<d who="bets">BETSY
<char who="trav">Travis</char>, you haven't even played the
record?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="evasive">(evasive)</desc>
    Yeah, well my stereo player is broke.
But I'm sure the record is OK.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
Your stereo broke? God, I could hardly
stand that. I live on music.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I don't follow music much. I'd like
to though.
<desc par="secodn thought">(second thought)</desc>Honest.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
<desc par="pointing to album">(pointing to album)</desc>
    So you haven't heard this record
yet?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
No.
<desc par="sly smile">(sly smile)</desc>
    I thought maybe you could play it
for me on your player.</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy's</char> face backtracks a bit. Maybe she was wrong to go out
with this fellow she doesn't know.
She makes a polite laugh.
LATER. <char who="trav">Travis</char> and <char who="bets">Betsy</char> are in <loc>TIMES SQUARE</loc>, turning the
corner from Broadway to 42nd Street. <char who="trav">Travis</char> carries the
album under his arm.
They approach the garish marquee of a large midtown porno
theatre advertising "The Swedish Marriage Manual". The box
office is flanked on both sides by glass cages filled with
explicit publicity stills. Offending portions have been
blocked out with black tape.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> steps over to the window and buys two $5 tickets.
<char who="bets">Betsy</char>, befuddled, watches him. She doesn't know what to say.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> returns with the tickets.
<char who="bets">Betsy</char> still has not fully comprehended what is happening:</narr>
(CONTINUED)
43.
CONTINUED:
<d who="bets">BETSY
What are you doing?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="innocent">(innocent)</desc>
    I bought a couple of tickets.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
But this is a porno movie.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
No, these are the kind that couples
go to. They're not like the other
movies. All kinds of couples go.
Honest. I've seen them.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> seems confused. He is so much part of his own world,
he fails to comprehend another's world. Compared to the movies
he sees, this is respectable. But then there's also something
that <char who="trav">Travis</char> could not even acknowledge, much less admit:
That he really wants to get this pure white girl into that
dark porno theatre.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> makes an awkward gesture to escort <char who="bets">Betsy</char> into the
theatre. <char who="bets">Betsy</char> looks at the tickets, at the theatre, at
<char who="trav">Travis</char>. She mentally shakes her head and walks toward the
turnstile. She thinks to herself: "What the Hell. What can
happen?" She's always been curious about these pictures
anyway, and - like all women, no matter how intelligent -
she's been raised not to offend her date. A perverse logic
which applies even more in offsetting circumstances like
these.
<loc>INSIDE THE THEATER</loc><char who="trav">Travis</char> escorts <char who="bets">Betsy</char> to an empty center row. <char who="trav">Travis</char> was right.
Couples do go to films like this. There are at least six or
seven other <char who="side">MEN</char> with their bewigged <char who="side">"DATES"</char>.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> settles into his familiar porno theatre slouch. <char who="bets">Betsy</char>
looks curiously from side to side.
ON SCREEN, a conservatively-dressed middle-aged woman is
speaking in Swedish about importance of healthy sex life in
a happy marriage. Subtitles translate her words. Then,
without warning, there is a direct CUT to a couple copulating
on a sterile table-like bed.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> watches intently. The color, however, is slowly
draining from <char who="bets">Betsy's</char> cheeks. One thought fills her mind:
"What am I doing here?"</narr>
(CONTINUED)
44.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="to himself">(to himself)</desc>
Damn.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
What's wrong?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I forgot to get the Coca-Cola.</d>
<narr>That does it. <char who="bets">Betsy</char> just looks at him for a moment, then
gets up and starts to leave. <char who="trav">Travis</char>, confused, hustles after
her.
He follows her out of the theatre.</narr>
<loc>ON THE SIDEWALK</loc><char who="trav">Travis</char> catches up with her.
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Where are you going?</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
I'm leaving.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
What do you mean?</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> looks at <char who="trav">Travis</char>, trying to understand him:</narr>
<d who="bets">BETSY
These are not the kind of movies I
go to.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Well, I don't follow movies too
much...</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
You mean these are the only kind of
movies you go to?</d>
<narr>The <char who="side">TICKET GIRL</char> watches expressionlessly from the booth.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
This is sort of high class...</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
I mean porno movies.</d>
(CONTINUED)
45.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="hesitant">(hesitant)</desc>
Well... mostly...</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
My God!</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
We can go to another movie if you
like, I don't care. I got money.
There's plenty...</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> gestures toward the long row of 42nd Street marquees,
but is interrupted by <char who="bets">Betsy</char>:</narr>
<d who="bets">BETSY
If you just wanted to fuck, why didn't
you just come right out and say it?</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> is flabbergasted by <char who="bets">Betsy's</char> blunt language. His arm
still gestures toward the marquees, his lips continue to
move, but words do not come out.
Unable to respond to <char who="bets">Betsy's</char> question, <char who="trav">Travis</char> picks up where
he left off:</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
... there's plenty of movies around
here. I haven't seen any of them,
but I'm sure they're good.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
No, <char who="trav">Travis</char>. You're a sweet guy and
all that, but I think this is it.
I'm going home.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="interrupting">(interrupting)</desc>
You mean you don't want to go to a
movie?
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
There's plenty of movies around here.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
No, I don't feel so good. We're just
two very different kinds of people,
that's all.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="puzzled">(puzzled)</desc>
Huh?</d>
(CONTINUED)
46.
CONTINUED:
<d who="bets">BETSY
It's very simple. You go your way,
I'll go mine. Thanks anyway, <char who="trav">Travis</char>.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
But... <char who="bets">Betsy</char>...</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
I'm getting a taxi.</d>
<narr>She walks to the curb.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="following her">(following her)</desc>
What about the record?</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
Keep it.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Can I call you?</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> looks for a cab.</narr>
   <d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="tender">(tender)</desc>
    Please, <char who="bets">Betsy</char>, I bought it for you.</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> looks at his sad, sweet face and relents a bit.</narr>
<d who="bets">BETSY
All right, I'll accept the record.</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> accepts the record, but quickly turns and hails a taxi.</narr>
<d who="bets">BETSY
Taxi!</d>
<narr>A taxi quickly pulls up.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> feebly protests to no one in particular:</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
But I got a taxi.</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> gives instructions to <char who="side">CAB DRIVER</char>, looks briefly back
at <char who="trav">Travis</char>, then straight ahead. Taxi speeds off.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> looks around helplessly: A cluster of <char who="side">PEDESTRIANS</char> on
the crowded street has stopped to watch the argument. <char who="trav">Travis</char>
(CONTINUED)
47.
CONTINUED:
looks back at the woman in the porno theatre box office who
has also been following the argument.</narr>
</scene>
        
<scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
<loc int="true">INSIDE TRAVIS' APARTMENT</loc>
<char who="trav">Travis</char> is sitting at the table. There are some new items on
the table: His giant econo-sized bottle of vitamins, a giant
econo-sized bottle of aspirins, a pint of apricot brandy, a
partial loaf of cheap white bread.
On the wall behind the table hang two more items: A gag sign
reading "One of These Days I'm Gonna Get Organezizied" and
an orange-and-black bumper sticker for <char who="pal">Charles Palantine</char>.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
May 8, 1972. My life has taken another
turn again. The days move along with
regularity...</d>
<narr><desc shot="close">C.U. of notebook</desc>: <char who="trav">Travis</char> is no longer sitting at the desk.
The pencil rests on the open notebook.
</narr>
        </scene>
            
        <scene>
<narr>LATER THAT DAY: <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> has pulled his straight-backed chair
around and is watching his small portable TV, which rests on
the upright melon crate.
A cereal bowl partially filled with milk rests in his lap.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> pours a couple shots of the apricot brandy into the
bowl, dips folded chunks of white bread into the mixture,
and eats them.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> is watching early evening NEWS PROGRAM. TV background
SOUND. <char who="pal">Charles Palantine</char> is being interviewed somewhere on
the campaign trail.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
... one day indistinguishable from
the next, a long continuous chain,
then suddenly - there is a change.</d>
<narr><char who="bets">Betsy</char> is walking down a midtown street when <char who="trav">Travis</char> suddenly
appears before her. He has been waiting.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> tries to make conversation but she doesn't listen.
She motions for him to go away and keeps on walking.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
48.
CONTINUED:
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char>, protesting, follows.
CUT TO:
<loc int="true">INT. BUILDING</loc> - DAY
<char who="trav">Travis</char> speaks intensely into a wall pay phone.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
I tried to call her several times.</d>
<narr>We hear <char who="trav">Travis'</char> Voice on the phone.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="smoking a cigarette">(smoking a cigarette)</desc>
you feeling better? You said you
didn't feel so good...</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
But after the first call, she would
no longer come to the phone.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> holds the receiver in his hand. The other party has
hung up.
<desc shot="tracking">TRACKING SHOT across interior lower wall of <loc int="true">TRAVIS' APARTMENT</loc>.</desc>
Against the stark wall there is a row of wilted and dying
floral arrangements. Each one of the four or five bouquets
is progressively more wilted than the one closer to the door.
They have been returned.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
I also sent flowers with no luck. I
should not dwell on such things, but
set them behind me. The smell of the
flowers only made me sicker.
The headaches got worse I think I've got stomach cancer. I
should not complain so. "You're only as healthy as you feel."</d>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>A drama is acted out at <loc>PALANTINE HEADQUARTERS</loc>: <char who="trav">Travis</char>,
groggy and red-eyed from lack of sleep, walks into the
campaign headquarters about NOONTIME.
<char who="bets">Betsy</char> is standing near the rear of the office; she ducks
from sight when she sees <char who="trav">Travis</char> enter. <char who="trav">Travis'</char> path is cut
short by <char who="tom">Tom's</char> large-framed body. There is no live sound.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
49.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
I realize now how much she is like
the others, so cold and distant.
Many people are like that. They're
like a union.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> tries to push his way past <char who="tom">Tom</char> but <char who="tom">Tom</char> grabs him.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> says something sharply to <char who="tom">Tom</char> and the two scuffle.
<char who="tom">Tom</char>, by far the taller and stronger, quickly overcomes <char who="trav">Travis</char>,
wrenching his arm behind his back.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> kicks and protests as <char who="tom">Tom</char> leads him to the front door.
<loc>ON THE SIDEWALK</loc>
<char who="trav">Travis'</char> efforts quickly subside when <char who="tom">Tom</char> motions to a nearby
<char who="side">POLICEMAN</char>. <char who="trav">Travis</char> quiets down and walks off.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
EXT.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> is again making his way through the garish urban night.
He stops for a <char who="side">PASSENGER</char> on <loc>PARK AVE.</loc> A middle-aging
professorial executive.
<desc shot="close">C.U. TRAVIS</desc>: His face is expressionless. The MAN makes
himself comfortable in the back seat.
<d who="side">PROFESSIONAL PASSENGER
Jackson Heights.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> has no intention of driving out to Jackson Heights
and coming back with a fare.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I'm off duty.</d>
<d who="side">PROFESSIONAL PASSENGER
You mean you don't want to go out to
Jackson Heights?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
No, I'm off duty.</d>
<d who="side">PROFESSIONAL PASSENGER
Then how come your "Off Duty" light
wasn't on.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> switches on the "Off Duty" light.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
50.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
It was on.
<desc par="gesturing toward top of taxi">(gesturing toward top
of taxi)</desc>
it just takes a while to warm up.
Like a TV.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> doesn't budge. <char who="side">PROFESSIONAL PASSENGER</char> curses to himself
and exits cab. <char who="trav">Travis</char> takes off.
<desc shot="pov">POV as <char who="trav">Travis'</char> eyes dwell on the young <char who="side">HIP COUPLES</char> coming
out of a East Side movie house.</desc></narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>LATER THAT NIGHT, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pulls over for a <char who="side">young (midtwenties) MAN</char> wearing a leather sports jacket.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> eyes his passenger in rear-view mirror.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
471 Central Park West.</d>
EXT.
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS'</char> taxi speeds off.
LATER, <char who="trav">TRAVIS'</char> taxi slows down as it approaches 400 block of
Central Park West.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> checks apartment numbers.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
Just pull over to the curb a moment.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> turns the wheel.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
Yeah, that's fine. Just sit here.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> waits impassively. The motor ticks away.
After a long pause, the <char who="side">PASSENGER</char> speaks:</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
Cabbie, ya see that light up there
on the seventh floor, three windows
from this side of the building?</d>
<narr><desc shot="tracking" shot="close">CAMERA CLOSES IN on 417 Central Park West: TRACKING UP to
the seventh floor, it moves three windows to the right.</desc></narr>
<d who="trav"><typo>TRAVIS (V.O.)
Yeah.</typo></d>
(CONTINUED)
51.
CONTINUED:
<narr>A young <char who="side">WOMAN</char> wearing a slip crosses in front of the light.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER (O.S.)
Ya see that woman there?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (O.S.)
Yeah.</d>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER (O.S.)
That's my wife.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
But it ain't my apartment.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
A nigger lives there.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
She left me two weeks ago. It took
me this long to find out where she
went.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
I'm gonna kill her.</d>
<narr><desc shot="close">C.U. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' face</desc>: it is devoid of expression.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
What do you think of that, cabbie?</d>
<narr><desc shot="close">C.U. <char who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER</char>'s face: it is gaunt, drained of blood,
full of fear and anger.</desc>
<char who="trav">Travis</char> does not respond.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
Huh?
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
What do you think of that, huh?</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> shrugs, gesturing toward meter.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER
I'm gonna kill her with a .44 Magnum
pistol.</d>
<narr><desc shot="panning">CAMERA returns to SEVENTH FLOOR WINDOW.</desc> Woman is standing in
the light.</narr>
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER (O.S.)
Did you ever see what a .44 can do
to a woman's face, cabbie?
<desc par="pause">(pause)</desc>
Did you ever see what it can do to a
woman's pussy, cabbie?</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> says nothing.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
52.
CONTINUED:
<d who="side">YOUNG PASSENGER (O.S.)
I'm going to put it right up to her,
cabbie. Right in her, cabbie.
You must think I'm real sick, huh?
A real pervert. Sitting here and
talking about a woman's pussy and a
.44, huh?</d>
<narr><desc shot="close">CAMERA CLOSES IN on <char who="trav">Travis'</char> face</desc>: He is watching the woman
in the seventh floor window with complete and total
absorption. It's the same glazed-over stare we saw in his
eyes as he watched the porno movie.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>FADE TO:
<loc ext="true">BROOKLYN STREET CORNER</loc> - DAY
<char who="trav">Travis</char> stands near the corner wearing his boots, jeans,
western shirt and army jacket.
He pulls his aspiring bottle out of his pocket, shakes three
or four into his palm, pops them into his mouth and chews.
An "Off Duty" taxi pulls up to the curb. <char who="trav">Travis</char> gets in.
<loc int="true">INSIDE TAXI</loc>
<char who="db">Dough-Boy</char> leans back from the wheel and greets <char who="trav">Travis</char> as he
enters.</narr>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
Hey <char who="trav">Travis</char>. This here's <char who="ez">Easy Andy</char>.
He's a travelling salesman.</d>
<narr>In the back seat, beside <char who="trav">Travis</char>, sits <char who="ez">ANDY</char>, an attractive
young man about 29. He wears a pin-striped suit, white shirt
and floral tie. His hair is modishly long.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Hello <char who="trav">Travis</char>.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> nods as the taxi speeds off.
<char who="db">Dough-Boy</char> slows down near an economy hotel. Not a flop house,
but not do fancy they care what the guests do in the privacy
of their rooms.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
This is fine, <char who="db">Dough-Boy</char>
<desc par="to Travis">(to Travis)</desc>
Pay <char who="db">Dough-Boy</char> here.</d>
(CONTINUED)
53.
CONTINUED:
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> pulls a twenty out of his pocket and gives it to <char who="db">DoughBoy</char>.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
20 bucks?</d>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
<desc par="takes bill">(takes bill)</desc>
Yeah. Hey thanks. That's real nice,
<char who="trav">Travis</char>.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> and <char who="ez">Andy</char> get out of the cab and walk toward the hotel.
<char who="db">Dough-Boy</char> pulls away.
As they enter the hotel, they pass a <char who="side">JUNKIE</char>, stoned out and
spread-eagled across the hood of a derelict old blue dodge.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr><loc int="true">INT. HOTEL</loc>
<char who="trav">Travis</char> follows <char who="ez">Andy</char> up the worn carpeted stairs and down the
hallway. <char who="ez">Andy</char> unlocks the door to one of the rooms.
The <loc int="true">HOTEL ROOM</loc> is barren and clean; there's no sign anyone
is staying in it. The fire escape is appropriately near.
<char who="ez">Andy</char> locks the door behind them, steps over to the closet,
unlocks it and pulls out two grey Samsonite suitcases - the
kind you can drive a truck over.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
<char who="db">Dough-Boy</char> probably told you I don't
carry any Saturday Night Specials or
crap like that. It's all out of
State, clean, brand new, top-ofthe-line stuff.</d>
<narr><char who="ez">Andy</char> places the suitcases on the white bedspread. The
suitcases are equipped with special locks, which he quickly
opens.
<char who="ez">Andy</char> opens the suitcases: Stacked in grey packing foam are
rows and rows of brand new hand guns.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
You got a .44 Magnum?</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
That's an expensive gun.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I got money.</d>
(CONTINUED)
54.
CONTINUED:
<narr><char who="ez">Andy</char> unzips a cowhide leather pouch to reveal a .44 Magnum
pistol. He holds it gingerly, as if it were a precious
treasure. Andy opens the chambers and cradles the long eightinch barrel in his palm. The .44 is a huge, oversize inhuman
gun.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
<desc par="admiringly">(admiringly)</desc>
It's a monster. Can stop a car --
put a bullet right into the block.
A premium high resale gun. $350 --
that's only a hundred over list.</d>
<narr><char who="ez">Easy Andy</char> is a later version of the fast-talking, goodlooking kid in college who was always making money on one
scheme or another. In high school he sold lottery tickets,
in college he scored dope, and now he's hustling hand guns.
<char who="ez">Andy</char> holds the Magnum out for <char who="trav">Travis'</char> inspection. There's a
worshipful <desc shot="close">CLOSEUP of the .44 Magnum</desc>. It is a monster.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> hefts the huge gun. It seems out of place in his hand.
It is built on Michelangelo's scale. The Magnum belongs in
the hand of a marble god, not a slight taxi driver. <char who="trav">Travis</char>
hands the gun back to <char who="ez">Andy</char>.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
I could sell this gun in Harlem for
$500 today - but I just deal high
quality goods to high quality people.
<desc par="pause">(pause)</desc>
Now this may be a little big for
practical use, in which case I'd
recommend the .38 Smith and Wesson
Special. Fine solid gun - nickel
plated. Snub-nosed, otherwise the
same as the service revolver. Now
that'll stop anything that moves and
it's handy, flexible. The Magnum,
you know, that's only if you want to
splatter it against the wall. The
movies have driven up the price of
the Magnum anyway. Everybody wants
them now. But the Wesson .38 - only
$250 - and worth every dime of it.
<desc par="he hefts the .38">(he hefts the .38)</desc>
Throw in a holster for $10.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> hefts the nickel-plated .38, points it out the window.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
55.
CONTINUED:
<d who="ez">ANDY
Some of these guns are like toys,
but a Smith and Wesson, man, you can
hit somebody over the head with it
and it will still come back dead on.
Nothing beats quality.
<desc par="pause">(pause)</desc>
You interested in an automatic?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I want a .32. Revolver. And a palm
gun. That .22 there.</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
That's the Colt .25 - a fine little
gun. Don't do a lot of damage, but
it's as fast as the Devil. Handy
little gun, you can carry it almost
anywhere. I'll throw it in for another
$125.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> holds the .32 Revolver, hefts it, slips it under his
belt and pulls his shirt over it. He turns from side to side,
to see how it rides in his waist.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
How much for everything.</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
The .32's $150 - and you're really
getting a good deal now - and all
together it comes to, ah, seven eightyfive for four pieces and a holster.
He'll, I'll give you the holster,
we'll make it seventy-five and you've
got a deal - a good one.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
How much to get a permit to carry?</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Well, you're talking big money now.
I'd say at least five grand, maybe
more, and it would take a while to
check it out. The way things are
going now $5.000 is probably low.
You see, I try not to fool with the
small-time crap. Too risky, too little
bread. Say 6 G's, but if I get the
permit it'll be as solid as the Empire
State Building.</d>
(CONTINUED)
56.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Nah, this'll be fine.</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
You can't carry in a cab even with a
permit - so why bother?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Is there a firing range around?</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Sure, here, take this card, go to
this place and give 'em the card.
They'll charge you, but there won't
be any hassle.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> pulls out a roll of crisp one hundred dollar bills
and counts off eight.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
You in Nam? Can't help but notice
your jacket?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="looking up">(looking up)</desc>
Huh?</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Vietnam? I saw it on your jacket.
Where were you? Bet you got to handle
a lot of weapons out there.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> hands <char who="ez">Andy</char> the bills. <char who="ez">Andy</char> counts them and gives <char who="trav">Travis</char>
a twenty and five.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Yeah. I was all around. One hospital,
then the next.</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
<desc par="through counting">(through counting)</desc>
It's hell out there all right. A
real shit-eatin' war. I'll say this,
though: It's bringing a lot of
fantastic guns. The market's flooded.
Colt automatics are all over.
<desc par="pockets the money">(pockets the money)</desc></d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="intensely">(intensely)</desc>
They'd never get me to go back.
They'd have to shoot me first.</d>
(MORE)
(CONTINUED)
57.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (CONT'D)
<desc par="pause">(pause)</desc>
You got anything to carry these in?
TRAVIS
<desc par="gestures to pistols">(gestures to pistols)</desc></d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> is like a light switch: For long periods he goes along
dark and silent, saying nothing; then suddenly, the current
is turned on and the air is filled with the electricity of
his personality. <char who="trav">Travis'</char> inner intensity sets <char who="ez">Andy</char> back a
bit, but he quickly recovers.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Sure.</d>
<narr><char who="ez">Andy</char> pulls a gym bag from under his bed. He wraps the gun in
the sheet in the bag and zips it up. An identical gym bag
can be partially seen under the bed. He hands <char who="trav">Travis</char> the
bag.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
You like ball games?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Huh?</d>
<d who="ez">ANDY
I can get you front and center.
What do you like? I can get you Mets,
Knicks, Rangers? Hell, I can get you
the Mayor's box.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Nah. I ain't interested.</d>
<narr><char who="ez">Andy</char> closes and locks the suitcases.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Okay, okay.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char> turns to leave.</narr>
<d who="ez">ANDY
Wait a second, <char who="trav">Travis</char>. I'll walk you
out.</d>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
58.
SEVERAL WEEKS LATER. The face of <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' apartment has
changed. The long, blank wall behind the table is now
covered with tacked-up charts, pictures, newspaperclippings, maps.
<desc shot="panning">CAMERA does not come close enough to discern the exact
contents of these clippings.</desc>
<desc shot="close"><char who="trav">Travis</char> is in C.U. in the middle of the floor doing push-ups.</desc>
He is bareback, wearing only his jeans. There is a long scar
across his left side.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
May 29, 1972. I must get in shape.
Too much sitting has ruined my body.
Twenty-five push-ups each morning, one hundred sit-ups, one
hundred knee-bends. I have quit smoking.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char>, still bareback, passes his stiff arm through the
flame of a gas burner without flinching a muscle.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
Total organization is necessary.
Every muscle must be tight.</d>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>       
<narr><loc int="true">INT. FIRING RANGE</loc>
The CRACKING SOUND of rapid-fire pistol shots fills the musty
air of the firing range. The walls are heavily soundproofed,
and sawdust is spread over the floor.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> stands rock solid, firing the .44 Magnum at an arm's
length. With each blasting discharge from the Magnum, <char who="trav">Travis'</char>
body shudders and shakes, his arm as if each recoil from the
giant gun was a direct attack on his masculinity.
<char who="trav">Travis</char> fires the Magnum as quickly as he can re-set, re-aim
and re-fire. The Magnum is empty, he sets it down, picks up
the .38 Special and begins firing as soon as he can aim.
After the .38, comes the .25: It is as if he were in a contest
to see how quickly he can fire the pistols. After all the
guns are discharged, he begins reloading them without a
moment's hesitation.
Downrange, the red and white targets have the black outline
of a human figure drawn over them. The contour-man convulses
under the steady barrage of <char who="trav">Travis'</char> rapid-fire shots. </narr>
59.
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr><loc int="true">INT. APARTMENT</loc>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, now wearing an unfastened green plaid western shirt,
sits at the table writing in his diary. The vial of bennies
is on the table.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
My body fights me always. It won't
work, it won't sleep, it won't shit,
it won't eat.</d>
<narr>LATER. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, his shirt still revealing his bare chest,
sits on his straight-backed chair watching the TV. The .44
Magnum rests on his lap.
The TV is Broadcasting ROCK TIME, a late afternoon local
teenage dance and rock show. On screen <char who="side">YOUNG TEENYBOPPERS</char>
are dancing, and the <char who="side">TV CAMERAMAN</char>, as any devotee of the
genre knows, is relentlessly ZOOMING-IN on their firm young
breasts, fannies and crotches -- a sensibility which reflects
<char who="trav">TRAVIS'</char> own. These supper-hour rock dance shows are the most
unabashedly voyeuristic form of broadcasting the medium has
yet developed.
The HARD ROCK NUMBER ends, and the TV CAMERA CUTS TO the
local <char who="side">DISC JOCKEY</char>, a hirsute plastic-looking man about 35.
FIVE scrumptious <char who="side">TEENYBOPPERS</char> are literally hanging on his
shoulders and arms, their faces turned up to him in droolish
awe. Out of his mouth comes an incessant stream of disc jockey
blather. He is the complete asshole; I don't know who is
currently performing this function in New York, but in Los
Angeles his name is Real Don Steele.</narr>
<d who="side">TV DISC JOCKEY
Freshingly, fantastic, freaked-out
dance time. Can you dig it? Dig on
it. You got it, flaunt it.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> watches the show, his face hard and unmoving. He is,
as the Scriptures would say, pondering all these things in
his heart. Why is it the assholes get all the beautiful young
chicks? He takes a swig of peach brandy.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
EARLY EVENING, about 6:30 p.m. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi, with 'Off
Duty' light on, sits near the curb somewhere in midtown
Manhattan.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> runs his hand down the left side of his jacket,
attempting to smooth out the bulge underneath. </narr>
(CONTINUED)
60.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> opens his jacket partially, checking underneath.
There rests the nickel-plated .38 Special in its holster.
<desc shot="pov">P.O.V. down the street where TRAVIS' taxi is parked</desc>: Several
blocks ahead the red, white and blue campaign headquarters
of <char who="pal">CHARLES PALANTINE</char> are visible.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS'</char> eyes resume their watch.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> starts the car and drives toward the <loc>PALANTINE
HEADQUARTERS</loc>.
<desc shot="tracking" shot="pov">TRACKING P.O.V. shot of row of storefronts leading up to
Palantine Headquarters. P.O.V. passes headquarters</desc>: it is
half-empty. A few stalwart <char who="side">SUPPORTERS</char> continue to work toward
the rear of the office. <char who="bets">BETSY'S</char> desk ----
Sign in window reads: "Only 4 More Days Until Arrival of
<char who="pal">CHARLES PALANTINE</char>."
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' "Off Duty" light goes off as he speeds up and heads
toward a prospective fare.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>LATER THAT NIGHT, about 9:30. <loc>UPTOWN -- 128th and
Amsterdam</loc>. The Jungle. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi pulls up to an
address, lets off <char who="side">YOUNG BLACK MAN</char>.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> receives fare and tip, takes off.
<desc shot="pov">P.O.V. as <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> works his way through Harlem back down
Seventh Ave</desc>. Cluster of <char who="side">YOUNG BLACK STREET PUNKS</char> pretend to
hail cab -- we ignore them. One throws wine bottle which
crashes in our path -- taxi swerves to avoid it.
<desc shot="tracking">CAMERA TRACKS through sidewalk <char>CROWDS</char> with the roving,
suspicious, antagonistic eye of a taxi-driver</desc>.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>LATER THAT NIGHT, about 12:30. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> is on the <loc>LOWER EAST
SIDE</loc>, somewhere on B Street, east of Tompkins Square.
The sidewalks are populated with the remains of what once
was the hippie movement: <char who="side">TEENAGE STREET-WALKERS</char>, <char who="side">JUNKIES</char>,
<char who="side">THUGS</char>, emaciated <char who="side">LONERS</char> on the prowl.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi pulls over, letting out a fare.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pockets his fare, but the rear right door doesn't
slam -- instead there is the SOUND of another person jumping
into the cab.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> checks the back seat in the rear-view mirror: there
sits a pale <char who="iris">HIPPIE PROSTITUTE</char>.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
61.
CONTINUED:
<narr>The <char who="iris">GIRL</char> is, at best, 14 or 15, although she has been made
up to look older. She wears floppy, Janis Joplin clothes.
Her face is pallid. She wears large blue-tinted sunglasses
and multi-colored leg stockings.
Her name, as we shall learn later, is <char who="iris">IRIS</char>.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> hesitates, looking at her in the mirror.
<d who="iris">IRIS
Come on, mister, let's get outta
here -- quick.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> moves to activate the meter, when the rear door opens.
<char who="iris">IRIS</char> is helped out of the cab by a <char who="sport">MAN TRAVIS cannot see</char>.</narr>
<d who="sport">SPORT
<desc par="to IRIS">(to IRIS)</desc>
Come on, baby, let's go. This is
all a real drag.</d>
<narr><char who="iris">IRIS</char> lets herself be taken out of the cab. The rear door
closes.
<char who="sport">Sport</char> leans partially in the front window, throwing something
on the front seat. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> looks: it is a crumpled $20 bill.</narr>
<d who="sport">SPORT
Just forget all about this, cabbie.
It's nothing.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> cannot see the <char who="sport">Sport's</char> face lime green completely,
but notices he is wearing a jacket. The voice is that of a
man in his early twenties.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> turns to catch a glimpse of <char who="sport">Sport</char> as he walks off
with <char who="iris">Iris</char>.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> shrugs and turns around.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi pulls away.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
EARLY MORNING, 6:00 a.m. Quitting time -- <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pulls into
<loc>TAXI GARAGE</loc>.
<loc int="true">INT. GARAGE</loc>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pulls into his stall.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
62.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> sits in driver's seat, thinking a moment. He looks
to his right: the crumpled $20 bill still lies there,
untouched since it was thrown there six hours previously.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> reluctantly picks up the $20 bill and stuffs it into
his jacket pocket as he gets out of the cab. He gathers up
his time report and heads toward book-in table.
A SHORT WHILE LATER, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> is walking down the sidewalk
near the taxi garage. His hands are in his jacket pockets,
obscuring the slight bulge on his left side.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> turns into the box offfice of <loc>PORNO THEATER</loc>. He
reaches into jacket pocket for money to purchase ticket and
pulls out crumpled $20 bill. Seeing the $20 bill, he decides
not to use it, and pays for ticket out of his wallet instead.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> walks past concession stand en route to the darkened
theater auditorium. A <char who="side">YOUNG MAN</char> is now sitting listlessly
behind the concessions counter.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr><loc int="true">INT. PORNO THEATER AUDITORIUM</loc>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> slouches down into his seat, his face glowing in the
reflected light from the screen.</narr>
<d who="side">FEMALE MOVIE VOICE (O.S.)
Oh, come on, now, down, lick it,
come on...
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
Mmm, that's good. Ahh, ahh, more
...</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> averts his eyes as the action on screen becomes too
graphic. Placing his stiffened right hand beside his eyes,
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> can, by turning it inward, shut off or open up his
field of vision by small degrees.
MOVIE VOICE DIMINISHES, replaced by SOUND of <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' voice
over.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
The idea had been growing in my
brain...</d>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
<desc shot="tracking">TRACKING SHOT to wall of <loc>TRAVIS' APARTMENT</loc>. CAMERA MOVES
slowly across wall covered with clippings, notes, maps,
pictures</desc>. We now see their contents clearly: </narr>
(CONTINUED)
63.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
The wall is covered with <char who="pal">CHARLES PALANTINE</char> political
paraphernalia; there are pictures of him, newspaper articles,
leaflets, bumper stickers. <desc shot="panning">As the CAMERA MOVES along it
discovers a sketch of Plaza Hotel, Kennedy Airport and cutup sections of city maps with notations written in</desc>. There
is lengthy N.Y. Times clipping detailing the increased Secret
Security Protection during the primaries. A section
pertaining to <char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> is underlined. Further along there
is a sheet reading "traveling schedule" and a calendar for
June with finely written notations written over the dates.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
... for some time. True Force.
All the king's men cannot put it
back together again.</d>
<narr><desc shot="tracking">As the CAMERA reaches the end of its track, it finds <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>,
standing, his shirt open, but the mattress</desc>. He is wearing
the empty holster, and the .44 is in his hand.
In the SHOTS that follow <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> gives the audience a lesson
in gunmanship:
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> practices fast-drawing the .38 Special from his holster
and firing it.
He hooks the .44 into his pants behind his back and practices
withdrawing it. He holds the .44 firmly at an arm's length,
tightening his forearm muscles.
He has worked out a system of metal gliders taped to his
inner forearm, whereby the Colt .25 can rest hidden behind
the upper forearm until a spring near the elbow is activated,
sending the .25 flying down the gliders into his palm. He
has cut open his shirt to accomodate the gun mechanism and
now checks in the mirror to see how well the gun is hidden.
He straps an Army combat knife to his calf and cuts a slit
in his jeans where the knife can be pulled out quickly.
He now tries on various combinations of shirts, sweater and
jacket in front of the mirror to see how well he can hide
all the handguns he wishes to carry. Finally, wearing two
western shirts, a sweater and jacket, he manages to obscure
the location of all three guns, although he resembles a hunter
bundled up against the Arctic winter.
He sits at the table dum-dumming the .44 bullets -- cutting
"x's" across the bullet heads.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
64.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
<desc shot="pov">P.O.V.: he scans the objects of his room through the scope
of the .38.</desc>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> stands in the middle of his apartment, staring at his
<char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> wall. His eyes are glazed with introspection; he
sees nothing but himself.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
Listen you screwheads: Here is a
man...</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> lies on his mattress, all bundled up in his shirts,
sweater, jacket and guns. His face is turned toward the
ceiling, but his eyes are closed. Although the room is
flooded with light, he is finally catching some sleep.
The big furry animal drifts into his own world.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
... who wouldn't take it any more, a
man who stood up against the scum,
the cunts, the dogs, the filth.
Here is ...
<desc par="voice trails off">(voice trails off)</desc></d>
<narr><desc shot="close">C.U. of diary</desc>: entry ends with words
"Here is" followed by erratic series
of dots.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
NIGHT: the taxis are roaming the slick streets.
Sometimes after 2:00 a.m., <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pulls his cab to the curb
near an all-night delicatessen in Spanish Harlem. The streets
are relatively deserted.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> waves to <char who="melio">STOREKEEPER</char> as he walks past counter:</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Hey 'Melio.</d>
<narr>Spanish rhythm and blues blares from a cheap radio.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> walks over to dairy counter in rear of store, picks
out a pint of chocolate milk, goes over to the open cooler
and picks through various chilled prepackaged sandwiches.
He overhears a VOICE as he looks at the sandwiches.
When <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> returns to the counter with the chocolate milk
and a sandwich in one hand, he sees a <char who="side">YOUNG BLACK MAN</char> holding
a gun on 'Melio.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
65.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
The <char who="side">STICK-UP MAN</char> is nervous, hopped-up, or both; he bounces
on the balls of his cheap worn black tennis shoes -- a strungout junkie on a desperation ride. The <char who="side">STICK-UP MAN</char>, a
thorough unprofessional, doesn't notice <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>.
'<char who="melio">MELIO</char> watches the <char who="side">STICK-UP MAN</char> closely, deciding what to do
himself.</narr>
<d who="side">STICK-UP MAN
<desc par="shaking gun">(shaking gun)</desc>
Come on, man. Quick, quick, quick.
Hand over that bread.</d>
<narr>It doesn't take <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> long to decide what to do: without
hesitation he pulls his .32 from his jacket pocket.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Hey dude!</d>
<narr>The <char who="side">STICK-UP MAN</char>, surprised, turns toward <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, finding
only an exploding .32. The <char who="side">MAN</char>'s lower jaw bursts open with
blood as he reels and crashes to the floor. There is no
emotion on <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' face.
As the <char who="side">STICK-UP MAN</char> falls, '<char who="melio">MELIO</char> leans over the counter,
wielding his battered .38. He is about to fire when he
realizes the <char who="side">MAN</char> is already dead.
'<char who="melio">MELIO</char>, charged up, turns his gun toward <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, then,
realizing the danger is over, lowers it again.</narr>
<d who="melio">'MELIO
Thanks, man. Figured I'd get him on
the way out.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> sets his .32 on the counter.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
You're gonna have to cover me on
this one, <char who="melio">'Melio</char>. I can't stay for
the cop show.</d>
<d who="melio">'MELIO
You can't do that, <char who="trav">Travis</char>. You're
my witness.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
The hell I can't. It's no sweat for
you. What is this for you, number
five?</d>
<narr><char who="melio">'MELIO</char> smiles and holds up four fingers:</narr>
(CONTINUED)
66.
CONTINUED:
<d who="melio">'MELIO
No, only four.
<desc par="shrug">(shrug)</desc>
Alright, <char who="trav">Travis</char>, I'll do what I can.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Thanks a lot.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> exits. '<char who="melio">MELIO</char> picks up the phone and starts dialing.
The bloody BODY lies on the floor unmoving.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, still carrying his pint of chocolate milk and
sandwich, walks down the empty sidewalk and enters his cab.
The street is deserted.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
DIRECT CUT TO PORNOGRAPHIC MOVIE: this is the first time we
have actually seen the porno movie itself.
<char who="side">SEVERAL ACTORS and ACTRESSES</char> are dallying on screen in
whatever manner the ratings board deems permissible.
Whatever the action, the movie's decor is strictly Zody's --
ersatz landscape paintings, tufted bedspreads. As in most
porno films, the <char who="side">ACTORS</char> look up occasionally toward the CAMERA
to receive instructions. Studio grunts, groans and moans of
pleasure have been dubbed in.
Action on screen begins to go into SLOW MOTION, the ACTORS
and ACTRESSES gradually transforming obscenity into poetry.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, sitting in his chair in his APARTMENT, watching
afternoon soap opera. He is cleaning his .38 and eating
from a jar of applesauce. Soap opera audio continues.
He watches the soap opera without expression.
SOUND TRACK of film also SLOWS DOWN, gradually mixing with
and then becoming the sound track of a midafternoon TV soap
opera.
A YOUNG GIRL and BOY are talking in those familiar soap opera
voices and a third party, the GIRL's mother, who had tried
to terminate their "relationship."
CUT TO: </narr>
(CONTINUED)
67.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
TELEVISION: The BOY is visiting the GIRL in her hospital
room. Both look as if they've stepped out of the Blue Chip
stamp catalogue.</narr>
<d who="side">SOAP OPERA BOY
Is it that she just doesn't -- like
me?</d>
<d who="side">SOAP OPERA GIRL
<desc par="hesitantly">(hesitantly)</desc>
Well, Jim, it's just that -- I don't
know how to say this -- it's that
she thinks your parents aren't...
good enough, I guess.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, through cleaning his gun, begins to play a game with
the television set.
He places the heel of his boot at the top of the melon crate
which supports the TV. Then, slowly rocking his heel back
and forth, he sees how far he can tip the melon crate without
knocking it over.
The TV, still broadcasting the hospital room melodrama, rocks
back and forth.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pushes the TV farther and farther until finally the
inevitable happens -- the crate tips backward, sending the
portable TV crashing to the floor.
There is a short flash and the TV screen turns white.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>, realizing what he has done, bends over, turns the TV
upright on the floor, fiddles with the knobs, slaps it, and
tries to reactivate the vanished image. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' efforts are
futile; a tube has broken, and the TV will not come back to
life.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="to himself">(to himself)</desc>
Damn, damn.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> bends over in the chair and places his head in his
hands, despairing of himself.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>FADE TO:
About 1 a.m. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> pulls his cab behind a line of empty
taxis parked outside the Bellmore Cafeteria, a cabbie hangout
on Park Avenue South.
He locks his cab and walks past the line of taxis. He
sidesteps <char who="side">TWO DRUNKEN FIGHTING BUMS</char> and enters the Bellmore.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
68.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
A LOUD BUZZER RINGS as <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> steps <loc int="true">INTO THE BELLMORE</loc>. He
pulls a ticket from the dispenser <desc par="silencing the buzzer">(silencing the buzzer)</desc> and
walks toward the wall-length counter.
An assortment of <char who="side">CABBIES</char> are seated around a formica-topped
table near the rear of the cafeteria. Some are barely awake,
some are eating, the rest are swapping stories and smalltalk.
<char who="wiz">Wizard</char>, <char who="db">Dough-Boy</char>, <char who="CT">Charlie T</char> and a <char who="side">FOURTH CABBIE</char> are seated
at a long table.</narr>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
You know Eddie, he's the new hippie
kid in our group, long hair...</d>
<narr><char who="wiz">Wizard</char> demonstrates length of hair and others nod.</narr>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
...he called up the Dispatcher last
night. Charlie McCall, our
dispatcher...</d>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
One-Ball McCall?</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
That's the guy. Eddie calls him up
and says, "Hey, what do you want me
to do. I'm over here at Poly Prep.
I got a girl in the back and she
doesn't have the fare. She wants me
to come in back and collect.
What should I do?</d>
<narr>The cabbies laugh. Across the cafeteria <char who="trav">Travis</char> selects a
cup of coffee and some pastries.</narr>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
This is on the two-way with about a
hundred and fifty cars listenin in.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
McCall says. "How much on the meter?"
Eddie comes back and says "Two-fifty."
McCall says, "Is she worth it".</d>
<narr>More laughter.</narr>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
Fuckin One-Ball.</d>
(CONTINUED)
69.
CONTINUED:
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
And the kid says, "Yeah. She's about
19, good-lookin." McCall says, "What
can I tell you?"</d>
<d who="side">FOURTH CABBIE
She should have told him to get an
OK from the front office.
<desc par="laughter">(laughter)</desc></d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
McCall says, "Well, if you want some
help I'll see if I can send some
units out."</d>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
Yeah. About a hundred and fifty.</d>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
I hope he had a checker.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
She was just a kid. Stoned, you
know.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">Travis</char>, carrying his coffee and pastries, walks over to their
table. <char who="ct">Charlie T</char> spots him.</narr>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
Hiya Killer.</d>
<narr><char who="ct">Charlie</char> forms his hand into a pistol, cocks and fires, making
the SOUND, "Pgghew." <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> nods.</narr>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
You're getting a rep, <char who="trav">Travis</char>.</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> sits down and the other <char who="side">CABBIES</char> resume their
conversation.</narr>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
Got the five you owe me, Killer?</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> reaches into his pocket and pulls out a roll of small
denomination bills. The crumpled $20 bill falls onto the
table. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> stares at it a moment. He unfolds a five,
gives it to <char who="ct">CHARLIE T</char>, then picks up the crumpled $20 and
puts it back into his jacket pocket.</narr>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD (O.S.)
<desc par="to Travis">(to Travis)</desc>
What's the action around?</d>
(CONTINUED)
70.
CONTINUED:
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Slow.</d>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
Shit yes. Night woulda been dead if
I hadn't grabbed an outatowner at
Kennedy. Took him roun the horn and
got a five dollar tip to boot.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
<desc par="joking">(joking)</desc>
One of these days we're gonna turn
you in, <char who="ct">Charlie T.</char> Fleecin the hicks
like that.</d>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
Remember the time this cat picks up
four dudes from the other side,
Pakastanis I think they were, holds
up their passports, to the toll booth
collector on the bridge and charges
em ten bucks each for 'crossing the
border?</d>
<narr>They all laugh.</narr>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
Hell, I know'd you to do worse.</d>
<d who="db">DOUGH-BOY
Least I'm no airport rat. I work
the whole town.</d>
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
<desc par="chuckling">(chuckling)</desc>
It's a living.</d>
<narr><cha who="wiz">WIZARD</char> gets up to leave.</narr>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
Well, I'm shovin' on.</d>
<narr><char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> gets up, nods and walks toward the <char who="side">CASHIER</char>. After a
second's thought, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> calls to him:</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Hey <char who="wiz">Wiz</char>, just a second. I wanna
talk to you.</d>
<narr><char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> waits for <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> as he takes a final gulp of coffee
and catches up with him. <char who="ct">CHARLIE T</char> calls to <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> as they
go:</narr>
(CONTINUED)
71.
CONTINUED:
<d who="ct">CHARLIE T
See ya, Killer. Don't forget your
pea shooter.</d>
<narr><char who="ct">CHARLIE T</char> cocks his imaginary gun again, fires and chuckles.
<char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> and <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> nod goodbye, pay the <char who="side">CASHIER</char> and exit.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>EXT.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> follows <char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> out onto the sidewalk. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> follows
<char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> as he walks toward his cab. He has something on his
mind, something he wants to talk to <char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> about.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="walking">(walking)</desc>
Hey <char who="wiz">Wiz</char>.</d>
<narr><char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> leans back against the cab. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> is about to speak
when he spots a <char who="side">GROUP of BLACK and PUERTO RICAN STREET PUNKS</char>,
ages 12-15, jiving down the sidewalk toward him. ONE tosses
a spray paint can around his back, basketball style.
ANOTHER mocks as if he's going to scratch a key along one of
the cabs.
<char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> has no visible reaction. A flash of controlled anger
crosses <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' face. He stares at the BOY with the poised
key. It is the same look that crossed his face in the Harlem
Deli. We are reminded with a jolt that the killer lies just
beneath <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' surface.
The <char who="side">BLACK PUNK</char> must instinctively realize this too, because
he makes a cocky show of putting the key back into his pocket
and be-bopping around <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> and <char who="wiz">WIZARD</char>.
The <char who="side">YOUNG MEAN-STREETERS</char> continue down the street and <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>
turns back to <char who="wiz">WIZARD</char>.
Across the street, in the background, a <char who="side">JUNKIE</char> nestles in a
doorway.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="hesitant">(hesitant)</desc>
<char who="wiz">Wiz</char>?</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
Yeah?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Look, ah, we never talked much, you
and me...</d>
(CONTINUED)
72.
CONTINUED:
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
Yeah?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I wanted to ask you something, on
account you've been around so long.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
Shoot. They don't call me the Wizard
for nothing.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Well, I just, you know...</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
Things got ya down?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Real down.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
It happens.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Sometimes it gets so I just don't
know what I'm gonna do. I get some
real crazy ideas, you know? Just go
out and do somethin.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
The taxi life, you mean.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Yeah.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
<desc par="nods">(nods)</desc>
I know.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Like do anything, you know.</d>
<d>WIZARD
<char who="trav">Travis</char>, look, I dig it. Let me
explain. You choose a certain way
of life. You live it. It becomes
what you are. I've been a hack 27
years, the last ten at night.
Still don't own my own cab. I guess
that's the way I want it. You see,
that must be what I am.</d>
(CONTINUED)
73.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
A police car stops across the street. <char who="side">TWO PATROLMEN</char> get out
and roust the <char who="side">JUNKIE</char> from his doorway.</narr>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
<desc par="continuing">(continuing)</desc>
Look, a person does a certain thing
and that's all there is to it. It
becomes what he is. Why fight it?
What do you know? How long you been
a hack, a couple months? You're
like a peg and you get dropped into
a slot and you got to squirm and
wiggle around a while until you fit
in.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
<desc par="pause">(pause)</desc>
That's just about the dumbest thing
I ever heard, <char who="wiz">Wizard</char>.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
What do you expect, Bertrand Russell?
I've been a cabbie all my life, what
do I know?
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
I don't even know what you're talking
about.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Neither do I, I guess.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
You fit in. It's lonely, it's rough
at first. But you fit in. You got
no choice.</d>
<d who="trav"><typo>WIZARD</typo>
Yeah. Sorry, Wizard.</d>
<d who="wiz">WIZARD
Don't worry, Killer. You'll be all
right.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
I seen enough to know.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Thanks.</d>
<narr><char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> gives <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> a short wave implying, "Chin up, old
boy," and walks around to the driver's side of his cab.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
74.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
<char who="wiz">WIZARD</char> drives off, leaving the street to its natural
inhabitants.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>       
<narr>CUT TO:
FADE IN:
<loc ext="true">EXT. CHARLES PALANTINE RALLY</loc> - DAY
A rally platform in a supermarket parking lot somewhere in
QUEENS is draped in red, white and blue bunting.
A <char who="side">CROWD</char> of about 500 persons mills about, waiting for the
rally to begin. Piped pop-country MUSIC plays over the
loudspeaker system.
The <char who="side">CADRE OF SECRET SERVICE MEN</char>, with their distinctive
metallic grey suits, sun glasses and football physiques,
stands out in the <char who="side">CROWD</char>.
On the PLATFORM are seated an assortment of <char who="side">LOCAL POLITICOS</char>
as well as some <char who="side">PALANTINE WORKERS and ADVISERS</char>.
<char who="tom">TOM</char> is silently reading something on the podium, and <char who="bets">BETSY</char>
stands on the platform steps talking with <char who="side">ANOTHER WORKER</char>.
<char who="tom">TOM</char> looks up and to his left for a moment, then returns to
what he was reading. Then he returns his gaze to the upper
left, watching something very closely.
After a moment he walks over to the steps where <char who="bets">BETSY</char> is
standing.</narr>
<d who="tom">TOM
<char who="bets">Betsy</char>, come over here a moment.</d>
<d who="bets">BETSY
What is it? I'm busy.</d>
<d who="tom">TOM
<desc par="insistent">(insistent)</desc>
Just follow me.</d>
<narr><char who="bets">BETSY</char> excuses herself and walks across the platform with
<char who="tom">TOM.</char>
As they stand to the rear of the platform, <char who="tom">TOM</char> secretively
makes a gesture with his eyes and says out of the side of
his mouth:</narr>
<d who="tom">TOM
Look there.</d>
(MORE)
(CONTINUED)
75.
CONTINUED:
<d who="tom">TOM (CONT'D)
<desc par="her eyes follow his">(her eyes follow his)</desc>
No, over further - get your glasses -
yes, over there. Isn't that little
guy the same guy that was bugging
you around the office about a month
ago?</d>
<narr><char who="bets">BETSY</char>, putting on her glasses, looks closely. She tries not
to make her stare too obvious.</narr>
<d who="bets">BETSY
No, I don't think so.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
That's someone else.</d>
<d who="tom">TOM
Now look more closely. Look around
the eyes and chin. See? See there?</d>
<narr><desc shot="close">CAMERA CLOSES IN on <char who="trav">TRAVIS BICKLE</char> standing in the <char who="side">CROWD</char></desc>: he
has shaved his head to a short stubble. There he is: brushcut, wearing a giant grin, and a large "Palantine '72" button.
Although it is a pleasant sunny day, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> wears a bulky
bulged-out Army jacket.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> looks warily from side to side and vanishes in the
<char who="side">CROWD</char>.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>A SHORT WHILE LATER, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> walks up to a <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN</char>
standing near the fringes of the <char who="side">CROWD</char>. The <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE
MAN</char> -- in sun glasses, grey suit, ever-roving eyes -- is
immediately identifiable.
Whenever <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> confronts a symbol of authority, he becomes
like a young boy. This time is no exception, although one
suspects there is a plan hatching beneath that boyish
exterior. The <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN</char>, for his part, is about as
talkative as the Sphinx.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Are you a Secret Service Man?</d>
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
<desc par="indifferently">(indifferently)</desc>
Why do you ask?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I've seen a lot of suspicious
looking people around here today.</d>
<narr><char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN</char> glances at <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> momentarily.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
76.
CONTINUED:
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
Who?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Oh, lots. I don't know where they
all are now. There used to be one
standing over there.
<desc par="points">(points)</desc></d>
<narr><char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN's</char> gaze follows <char who="trav">TRAVIS'</char> finger for a second,
then return to <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Is it hard to get to be a Secret
Service Man?</d>
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
Why?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I kinda thought I might make a good
one. I'm very observant.</d>
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
Oh?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
I was in the Army too.
<desc par="beat">(beat)</desc>
And I'm good with crowds.</d>
<narr>The <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN</char> is starting to get interested in
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>: he definitely ranks as a suspicious character.</narr>
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
Is that so?</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
What kind of guns do you guys use?
.38's?</d>
<narr>The <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN</char> decides it's time to get some more
information on <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>:</narr>
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
Look, um, if you give me your name
and address, we'll send you the
information on how to apply.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
You would, huh?</d>
(CONTINUED)
77.
CONTINUED:
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
<desc par="taking out notepad">(taking out notepad)</desc>
Sure.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
My name is Henry Krinkle -- that's
with a "K." K-R-I-N-K-L-E. I live
at 13 1/2 Hopper Avenue, Fair Lawn,
New Jersey. Zip code 07410.
<desc par="a beat">(a beat)</desc>
Got that?</d>
<d who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN
Sure, Henry. I got it all. We'll
send you all the stuff all right.</d>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS
Great, hey. Thanks a lot.</d>
<narr>The <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE MAN</char> motions to a <char who="side">SECRET SERVICE
PHOTOGRAPHER</char> to catch a picture of <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> notices
this, and quickly slips away into the <char who="side">CROWD</char>.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> sits at his desk in his <loc int="true">APARTMENT</loc>, writing. He wears
jeans, western shirt and empty holster.</narr>
<d who="trav">TRAVIS (V.O.)
June 11. Eight rallies in six more
days. The time is coming.</d>
<narr>CUT TO:
NIGHT. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi picks up a FARE in the midtown area and
heads downtown.
<loc>LOWER EAST SIDE</loc>. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> lets off FARE on B Street and cuts
across toward Tompkins Square.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> turns the corner when SKREETCH! he suddenly hits the
brakes, causing the cab to rock back and forth.
He has almost hit a <char who="iris">YOUNG GIRL</char> recklessly crossing the street.
She thumps her hand on the taxi hood to regain her balance
and stares in shock through the front window. <desc shot="close">C.U. GIRL's
face.</desc>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> recognizes her face: it's <char who="iris">IRIS</char>, the GIRL in his taxi
a week or so before. <char who="iris">IRIS</char> looks at <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> sharply then turns
and continues walking.</narr>
(CONTINUED)
78.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' eyes follow her and she rejoins a <char who="side">GIRLFRIEND</char>. They
are both dressed as hippie hookers: sloppy clothes, boots,
jeans, floppy hats. And the old come-hither walk is
unmistakable.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> follows <char who="iris">IRIS</char> and her <char who="side">GIRLFRIEND</char> slowly as they walk
down the sidewalk.
<desc shot="pov"><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' P.O.V. He examines them from bottom to top -- boots,
legs, thighs, breasts, faces, hats.</desc>
As <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> rolls astride the GIRLS, he notices the familiar
FRINGE OF A SUEDE JACKET standing in the shadows. The GIRLS
look toward the SHADOWED FIGURE, smile, acknowledge some
unheard comment, and continue on.
<char who="iris">IRIS</char> looks back uneasily at <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi and continues on.
On the corner stand TWO well-to-do <char who="side">COLLEGE STUDENTS</char>, somewhat
out of place in this environment, but making every attempt
to groove on it. They are high on something or another.
The GIRLS spot the <char who="side">COLLEGE STUDENTS</char> and walk over to them.
They exchange some small talk and walk off together. There
is little subtlety involved: it is obviously a pick-up.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> must negotiate a turn around the corner if he is to
continue following the GIRLS and their <char who="side">COLLEGIATE JOHNS</char>.
This is not so easy, since the traffic is heavy.
As <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> slows down to make the turn, he notices <char who="side">ANOTHER
HIPPIE HOOKER</char> who had been watching him watching <char who="iris">IRIS</char> and
her <char who="side">GIRLFRIEND</char>. She walks over to the taxi, loans in the
open left front window and gives <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> the come-on disguised
as an innocent question:
<desc shot="close">C.U. HIPPIE HOOKER</desc>.</narr>
<d who="side">HIPPIE HOOKER
Hey cabbie! You comin' or goin'?</d>
<narr><char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> quickly turns his face away from her in a combination
of shock, embarrassment and revulsion. He is the child caught
with his hand in the cookie jar. The very presence of this
crassly, openly sexual human being frightens and sickens
him.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> takes off with a skreetch. His taxi shoots down the
block.</narr>
        </scene>
        
        <scene>
<narr>CUT TO:</narr>
(CONTINUED)
79.
CONTINUED:
<narr>
A HOT JUNE DAY. <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>' taxi, the "Off Duty" sign on, is
parked against the curb somewhere in <loc>HARLEM</loc>. <char who="side">WHITE COPS</char>,
<char who="side">SECRET SERVICE MEN</char> and <char who="side">REPORTERS</char>, punctuate the otherwise
<char who="side">BLACK CROWDS</char> which walk to and fro in the b.g.
<char who="pal">CHARLES PALANTINE's</char> voice can be heard coming from a distant
loudspeaker system. It is a political rally.
<char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> sits behind the wheel, coldly staring at something in
the distance. His hair, of course, is still clipped short
and he wears mirror-reflecting sunglasses. Even though a
drop of sweat is working its way down his cheek, <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> wears
his Army jacket with the bulge on the left side -- the .38
Smith and Wesson bulge.
A BLOCK AWAY, <char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> stands on a platform outside his
uptown campaign headquarters. On the platform sit an array
of <char who="side">BLACK DIGNITARIES</char>. Nearby we recognize the <char who="ssman">SECRET SERVICE
MAN</char> <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char> spoke to at the earlier rally: he scans the <char who="side">CROWD</char>
anxiously.
<char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> is speaking animatedly. He is an excellent speaker
and captures our attention. He drives hard toward his
arguments, crashes down on his points. His strained voice
rings with sincerity and anger.
<desc shot="close">C.U. of <char who="pal">PALANTINE</char> as he speaks</desc>. He is dressed in rolled-up
shirtsleeves and sweat pours down his face.</narr>
<d who="pal">PALANTINE
The time has come to put an end to
the things that divide us: racism,
poverty, way -- and to those
persons who seek to divide us.
Never have I seen such a group of
high officials from the President to
Senate leaders to Cabinet members...</d>
<narr>CUT TO <char who="trav">TRAVIS</char>: no expression. <char who="pal">PALANTINE's</char> words are barely
distinguishable from a block away:</narr>
<d who="pal">PALANTINE
<desc par="in distance">(in distance)</desc>
... pit black against white, young
against old, sow anger, disunity and
suspicion -- and all in the name of
the "good of the country."
Well, their game is over.
<desc par="applause">(applause)</desc>
All their games are over.</d>
(MORE)
(CONTINUED)

<!--END PART 2-->

    </script>
</root>